[SPEAKER_01]: This is a continuation of Majjhima Nikaya No.
[SPEAKER_01]: 2.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'll just recap and continue sort of where we left off.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, the Buddha's just...
[SPEAKER_01]: This is a teaching, where he's teaching us how to restrain the asavas and how to abandon the asavas.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he began by saying that the destruction of these asavas, these defilements, is for one who knows and sees... for one who knows and sees attention with perspective or attention without... and what is attention without perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he knows the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then we went to the first way to abandon these defilements is by seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Pali word is dasana.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, defilements to be abandoned by dasana.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I looked it up and it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems to suggest that the word apperception is a good translation for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing, apperception.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're like observing things and then, over time, seeing where they rooted your actions and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you were saying the other day that this practice is basically about changing the significance of a thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, like, our perception is that, like, through the experience of certain perceptions, you get to understand more.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, next time you perceive the same thing, you don't have to go through the same motions of recollecting what you understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding, knowledge, becomes part of, now, that perception, becomes a significance of what you're seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not perceiving your knowledge,
[SPEAKER_00]: Directly, like it's not written in this thing, but because of the effort you made, the knowledge now becomes a significance of your perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: The knowledge is the result of perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perception comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having perceived, one then gets to develop knowledge about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once you know it, you don't need to keep telling yourself, oh, let me now get the knowledge of this which I'm perceiving, because perceiving it will mean that knowledge is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's... well, that's at least how I understand our perception, as a term.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... and, yeah, that knowledge is on the level of changing the significance of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, seeing a beautiful object,
[SPEAKER_00]: For a mind that's not trained, results in, basically, significance of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Significance of, oh, gratification of my pleasure, joy I can get if I have this beautiful object, fear of losing the beautiful object, you might have to protect it.
[SPEAKER_00]: All that is significance of seeing the beautiful object.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you've been practicing sensory strain long enough, understanding dhamma sufficiently enough, developing mindfulness to the extent necessary, perception of beautiful will be signifying danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will be signifying peril, like the Buddha said, like a... like a... what is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: The pit filled with burning embers.
[SPEAKER_00]: Charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, charcoal pit filled with burning embers.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the same centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now the man sees it, he sees for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if somebody, if two strong men would come and pick you up and carry you, to throw you in a charcoal pit, like your intention would be everywhere else.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would want to be anywhere else except there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't want to go into the pit of burning embers.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how the significance of sensuality must be developed in order for you to abandon sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to start seeing it as a charcoal pit full of burning embers.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind will completely, completely not want to even entertain it for a split second, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you cultivate that sufficiently enough, because sensuality is, factually, charcoal pit with burning embers, that will become apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like the danger became apparent, the escape became apparent, and all these things that we will talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the next time you see a sensual thing, that's that apperception.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not perceiving the beautiful anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still the same thing you're perceiving, by the way, but now your perception with that knowledge is seeing the danger and the ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have changed the significance of that perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've undone those significances of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because those significances were not set in stone.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they were, freedom from sensuality would not be possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were simply maintained through your perpetual engagement, careless engagement and ignorant engagement with desire and sense gratification.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you you kind of start off, obviously, full of lust and ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And seeing your body as a wonderful thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as a tool of getting more wonderful things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you need to... the practice is to resignify it, or take apart that significance there, by looking at it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in order for you to start seeing it for what it is, you need to start restraining your body first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're still regarding sensuality as beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like... that's one layer, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, acting out of body towards more gratification of sensuality, seeking more sensual object, that's another layer you add on top of the layer of your thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as long as any of those layers are there, you are fueling that misperception, that wrong significance, that mistaken notion of centrality as beautiful and non-harmful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to first start restraining the coarser layer, which is layer of physical action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you mentally still don't see a reason for it, and you're still attracted to it, and you still don't see it as dangerous or perilous, you need to restrain your body first, pretty much out of faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, until you get to understand it for yourself, and then you're the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, we said that many times before, you come with a horrible skin disease, it itches like hell, you go to see a doctor, the doctor gives you medicine, but says, well, before you start applying the medicine, you need to stop scratching it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it doesn't matter the amount of medicine you apply, the amount of your meditation you do, and suttas you read, if you keep scratching your itch, you are aggravating your condition.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he doesn't know that the doctor's medicine will help him.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way to find out is first, out of faith, to take it on trust, that he should stop scratching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, see, he has to take on faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: That the doctor is right and that scratching is the wrong thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's got to keep telling himself, in a way, to really believe the doctor.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this scratching is bad, rather than the scratching is good for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like you take this... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start rewriting the significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rewriting, rewriting, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take, basically, you take an external view, out of faith, and obviously some consideration.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to just be faithful.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to consider it, as we said before,
[SPEAKER_00]: I just blindly take it, but think about it, reason and see which is least likely to be wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is this doctor... is there a good chance that he might be right?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do I have to lose?
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like, oh, you follow this teacher to the end of the world and, like, for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take on his instruction until you're cured.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you won't need to have faith in him, because you're cured.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know that he was right.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no room for faith now.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's just confident that what you did on account of that instruction was correct.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even then, so you have to take it externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because your whole condition is affected with the disease, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you have no health reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Since you can remember, your skin was itching.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you take it on trust, externally, external point of view, saying, actually, if you stop scratching sufficiently enough, the time will come when you will heal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you value the prospect, the idea of healing, after, you know, thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you take it on trust.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whichever view you take on trust, is basically like, like grafting a tree.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take a completely different thing, and then you put it onto this tree, and if you cultivate it rightly enough, it will grow into the tree, and then it will become a new tree.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like how the grafting is done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you have the mix of the previous and the new tree, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to graft the view onto your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will then take over things, because they would... if the view was right, that you took, if the instruction was from the Buddha, for example, and you took it rightly, and you've been restrained, it will have to
[SPEAKER_00]: Take, like, you have to start growing correctly, because the view was right, and that means it corresponds to the universal nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Such as, sensuality was truly unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was truly burning embers.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was truly dissatisfactory.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you took that on trust, and then kept applying it, and kept applying it, and keeping the basis of restraint, and then it took root, because those were the exactly matching conditions for the view that you took.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you take the medicine, you follow the doctor's instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it doesn't work, well, you review it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it because I'm not restrained enough, honestly speaking?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it because... no, I'm completely restrained, I'm doing everything rightly, but this doesn't seem to be curing me of my itch.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, maybe I should look for another doctor.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then do the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you do want results.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't just take it on faith without any results whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, at the same time, don't forget that you don't really know what the right results are at that stage.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there has to be some time involved on... during which you're applying these things out of faith and confidence that it will help you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't happen overnight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it takes...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just to recap again.
[SPEAKER_01]: These defilements to be abandoned by seeing, by aperception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it says that an ordinary person does not understand what things are fit for attention and what things are unfit for attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Since that is so, he attends to things that are unfit for attention,
[SPEAKER_01]: And he does not attend to those things fit for attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what are the things unfit for attention that he attends to?
[SPEAKER_01]: They are things such that when he attends to them, the unarisen defilement of sensual desire arises, the defilement of being arises, and the defilement of ignorance arises, or increases.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, increases.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he doesn't see what the, you know, what he's attending to is actually causing him these problems.
[SPEAKER_01]: The way he's attending to things is making the farmers worse, increasing them, sustaining them, maintaining them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the noble disciple
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he attends to things with a perspective, he can see, ah, this...
[SPEAKER_00]: Suitable and unsuitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: This thing that I attend to now, which is kind of neutral maybe in itself, is actually increasing my sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you realize it's not neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the noble disciple then has this ability to see his mind
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about it in the same simile of the skin condition and the medicine from the doctor in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you know is itch.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't really know what's helpful, what's not helpful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start restraining, you start putting this cream on, you start not exposing it to sun, cleaning your wound, as the Buddha would say, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it starts getting better.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, you do recognize improvement for yourself, which means you don't need to keep reminding yourself of the faith you have in a doctor, because it's working.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're still not fully healed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that, that would be the equivalent of a noble disciple.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, from the point of view of partially healed wound and diminished itch, he knows exactly now, because that's now his criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, actually, this is now bringing back that old itch that was gone, that disappeared.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if I do this, then it's making it even less itchy than before.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's healing more or aggravating it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now he can know because he gained some perspective due to the actual healing of his skin condition.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the noble disciple would know what's fit for attention, what it isn't, because he actually sees it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, if I attend to this, that which hasn't healed yet, it's not gonna heal.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I attend to this, that which hasn't healed yet, is healing more.
[SPEAKER_01]: But also, ordinary people can sort of... can practice that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can see, well, if I... Well, you should be trying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm doing these actions and what is the result of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: More sensual desire, more, you know, distraction, dull-minded laziness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just... you won't have... you won't have a putujana
[SPEAKER_00]: You can, by all means, and should, by all means, be trying to emulate Sotāpanna, or higher, because that's how you have a chance of understanding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But don't confuse yourself into, like, believing that you are now, because, look, I'm doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what, what Putujananda will not have is the immediacy of that criteria that a noble disciple has.
[SPEAKER_00]: He immediately knows
[SPEAKER_00]: He might choose to ignore it, but it's visible, for him it's immediately visible, whether this is suitable or unsuitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: How unsuitable this is, or how suitable this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But Ujjaina doesn't have that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't have the immediacy of that criteria, which means he needs to invest more effort, like wider effort, into constantly recollecting the context of the danger that he took on faith, the context of avoiding this, cultivating that, what doctor told him.
[SPEAKER_00]: He needs to keep more in his mind, because he doesn't have the immediate verification that, oh, look, my wound's getting better, my wound's getting worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: For him, it's all worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he has no criteria that will come internally from the wound.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all like what he has adopted as views and faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's something like, as I said, the Noble Disciple doesn't need to remind himself anymore that the doctor knows what he's talking about, because his wound is... that's the significance of his wound now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Healing wound is basically the significance of a doctor was correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now he has got a criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows what healing is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: He sees it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He sees it now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now he can pick up the sign of unwholesome and wholesome immediately.
[SPEAKER_01]: In anything that he attends to.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by seeing that this is increasing defilements, he doesn't attend to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't go in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: He chooses the other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: He abandons the defilements because of that seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That direct seeing is the direct feedback.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, anyway, here it says that these three āsavas, these three defilements, sensual desire, being and ignorance, and just being, the defilement of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe you can briefly say what... Well, didn't we do the whole talk on that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Being, non-being, bhāva, vibhāva, yeah, being, existence, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any... Well, I don't want to get into that now, because that is... We did the whole talk on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But anything that increases being, ignorance...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's basically being is what you have left after you abandon sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are the three types of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: The central being, the material being, and the immaterial being.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there is a central being, being is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the coarsest type of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not only when you engage.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're not free from centrality, you're always... your being is on the plane of centrality, on the plane of the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, if you have abandoned centrality, then your being is on the plane of the presence of the form.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, if you abandon that, then your being is on the level of, you know, the absence of the form and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, that's just way too abstract for any practical application for somebody who will listen to this talk.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, practically speaking, whatever your current situation is,
[SPEAKER_00]: means it exists.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's present, as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has appeared.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means being is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're not an arahant, means there is a degree of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: And being means misconception, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whenever there is a being, there is appropriation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever there is a being, there is a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever there is a being, there is a sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: And vice versa.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever there is a sense of I am, means there is a degree of being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's... and this is saying that the Noble Disciple sees...
[SPEAKER_00]: He would see what would increase that and what wouldn't increase that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's... it's a bit coarse to say, oh, sense of self is what the being is, but practically speaking, it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no sense of being or existence that you can perceive apart from your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even in philosophy, people think they're talking about the pure being, independent of an individual.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a pure abstraction that's within their sense of self and being of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, being, bhāva, existence in philosophy, whatever you want to call it, whichever word you want to use, if you are honestly and like strictly looking at it as a phenomena, it's inseparable from the sense of self and your current situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why your current situation will either be on the level of kāma-bhāva, rūpa-bhāva or ārūpa-bhāva, depending on how much effort you made to abandon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, practically speaking, being bhava is that, being of I am, even if you don't explicitly think in terms of yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact is that your point of view already carries a degree of that self-centeredness and conceiving of I am, that being is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's subtler than I am such and such, but it's a kind of root of it anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to practically start thinking about being and trying to get a criteria what would increase the being, what would decrease the being, think from that, oh, the self-centeredness, the conceit, the I am, the self, the point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just reflecting on... Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Will this... Like again, is this pleasing to me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is this displeasing to me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why does that matter to me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, in a way, you realize that many, on many instances, you operate, like, throughout your life, just out of these, eh... things that infer from the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: To me and for me, it's like, yeah, but did I ever stop and think, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is this a problem for me, or why do I want this?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it just happened that my sense of self wanted this, that was providing me with gratification, and I never questioned it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, stop using your sense of self as a reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, to some extent, you're already shifting away from that, like, perpetuating that being with that wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the ultimate being that is used as a reference point is centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the first and foremost for most people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like pleasure, pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's literally the place, the self-centered, kind of the center from which they infer whether something is worth doing or not worth doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Will this provide me with pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or will this punish me with pain?
[SPEAKER_00]: But, so, if you stop using that center, you stop relying on Karmabhāva.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop relying on the central being.
[SPEAKER_00]: And instead, maybe you inform your perspective a bit more.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you say, well, sense restraint will hurt me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, but, you know, if it's to believe all these wise men, and even my own reasoning, I think there is a chance that it might heal my my wound of sensual itch, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, immediately, you're choosing pain, pretty much, which is against the criteria of your kammabhāva and what you are, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, so, see, you're not using that self-centered being of kamma, sensuality, as a reference point anymore, but are actually dissolving it into something more wholesome, something more informed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you abandon centrality, you have abandoned kama-bhāva, so your being bhāva has diminished to a great extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, there are subtler forms of bhāva, but again, you're unable to think about subtler forms of bhāva, unless you're already free from kama-bhāva, because whenever you think about all sorts of types of bhāva, you're thinking it through the framework of bhāva that you are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is, for most people, kāma-bhāva, because most people are not free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the lower noble disciples are not free from sensuality, so they're not free from that, from that bhāva yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, it says the ordinary person,
[SPEAKER_01]: This is how he attends unwisely or without perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: He asks questions internally, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Was I in the past?
[SPEAKER_01]: Was I not in the past?
[SPEAKER_01]: Having been, what did I become in the past?
[SPEAKER_01]: What shall I be in the future?
[SPEAKER_01]: Having been, what shall I become in the future?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or else, he's inwardly perplexed about the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, am I?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I not?
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I?
[SPEAKER_01]: How am I?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where has this being come from?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where will it go?
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a few more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I was saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, in that instance, just clearly shows how
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just that you're not free from the gratuitous self-centered sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am the center of the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, was I in the past?
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything is determined by you and whether you were and will you and are you going to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already completely gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, so even if you don't necessarily act out of that wrongly assumed center of sense of self,
[SPEAKER_00]: Entertaining these questions still perpetuates the centeredness of that gratuitous view.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why those are wrong questions, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because, oh, you know, you can never express what the true self is.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's simply because any of those questions still revolves around the assumption that that self is in the center and it's worth answering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Self-centered questioning point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, am I in the past?
[SPEAKER_00]: Was I in the past?
[SPEAKER_00]: Will I be in the future?
[SPEAKER_00]: Takes for granted that that self is the center of that whole experience and thus it's important for me to know was I in the past and will I be in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's actually irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is relevant is to stop being centered upon that self-center.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, mindfulness is already a way of cultivating and maintaining
[SPEAKER_00]: Or preventing yourself from becoming reabsorbed too deeply into that gratuitously assumed self-centered I am, that just basically always serves its own purpose.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you live... the noble disciple lives according to...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as it says, this is how he attends without perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he, this ordinary person, doesn't have that perspective of the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And thus, he thinks he's the center, he's the
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's, that's implicit.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's part of the significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't even need to think it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He needs to actively think the opposite, to eventually undo that significance.
[SPEAKER_01]: But one could do...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the Buddha says this, yet I'm doing this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let me have faith and do what he says, not what...
[SPEAKER_01]: I put myself second.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why faith, as blind as it is, always, in its nature, can be a factor that can, that can help somebody with the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in itself,
[SPEAKER_00]: But, exactly, if somebody out of faith, firm faith, decides to use Buddha's reference point from the suttas and not his reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I want to do this, the Buddha says you shouldn't do it, and I don't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you stick to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to take longer than if you make more active effort in terms of vipassana.
[SPEAKER_00]: But nevertheless, you are doing the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why there is the Sadhanussari type.
[SPEAKER_00]: The one, through faith, adopts certain behavior and sticks to it, and it goes against his entire grain of his being, but he sticks to it, and that being will evaporate sufficiently, and he becomes Sotāpanna, like Sadhanussari, that leads to the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, whether you... and for most people, it would be a combination of a bit of everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as we've said in the past, or I've said in the past as well, in the suttas it's clear,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like sexual activity needs to be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha says it.
[SPEAKER_01]: For the practice of dhamma, you cannot have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, for many people who go, yeah, but well, you know, hey, you know, you know, well, it's a case... Means they don't have enough faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if they did, they wouldn't even need to reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, some people need to reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: I personally need to reason or needed to reason things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Faith wasn't really working to that extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whichever way it is, you do need to start emulating that behavior, either on account of faith or on account of your reasoning, but you need to start doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like, oh, I have faith, the Buddha is the greatest, but does your behavior emulate what the great Buddha said or not?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or like, yes, I've reasoned everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha is perfectly right, again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does your behavior emulate now that rightness that you reasoned?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you will not bear the result.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's again like the simile the Buddha gave, like a hen that sits on her eggs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if she doesn't wish for the chicks to pierce, she is making the effort, doing the work and sitting on her eggs.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will come out safely and be born into this world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Alternatively, you have the hand that doesn't sit on her eggs, doesn't do the work, but she wishes that her chicks come out in this world.
[SPEAKER_00]: They won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wishing is irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you wish or not, it's basically whether you do it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's going to bear the results.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said that the dhamma and the practice and the results of dhamma are not to be obtained by the wishing alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can wish, and because of the wish, you start making the effort and sit on the eggs until they hatch.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you just wish and glorify your wish, as most people's faith practice these days is, you're not doing the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's exactly... Oh, I'm so devoted, I'm so proud, I'm so happy, I'm so inspired.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you keep the five precepts?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you keep the eight precepts?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you celibate?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you eat once a day?
[SPEAKER_00]: How much time do you spend in solitude?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you read the suttas?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, no, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I have such a great faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that faith is meaningless.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, I have a faith in this doctor.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, but I'm not neither abstaining from from scratching, neither covering it from the sun, neither cleaning it from the dust, neither applying the medicine.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just have a shrine that venerates this great doctor.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you cannot possibly expect to heal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just remind me, also, the person with faith, real faith, proper faith, he takes on that idea, he has that idea, the Buddha is the teacher, I am the disciple, is one of the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows what he's taught.
[SPEAKER_01]: I do not know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even though I believe this way, but he's saying to go this way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the Buddha is the teacher.
[SPEAKER_00]: If things are at odds, I know who's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If things are... yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So again, just to continue on that ordinary person, when he attends without perspective, one of six views arise in him.
[SPEAKER_01]: The self exists for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: No self exists for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I perceive self with self.
[SPEAKER_01]: I perceive not-self with self.
[SPEAKER_01]: I perceive self with not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is this self of mine that speaks and feels and experiences here and now the results of good and bad actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this self of mine is permanent, everlasting, eternal, not subject to change, and it will endure as long as eternity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, all of that is on the level of significance of your experience, of your self-centered experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are not explicitly thought that people will have in their mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will live forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody thinks that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, everybody is a victim of their view, unless you're a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what you need to understand when you read these suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, it's gonna make sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's like, yeah, but I don't partake on this level.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is for somebody who already understood, and he's describing how, when you boil down things, how they're seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Practically speaking, you don't see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are a victim already, of your own delusion, of your own ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, practically speaking, if you want to understand these six, basically, products, you should see that, what do they all have together, in common?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that self, it's basically, not a problem, but the result of a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your sense of self is a symptom.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a symptom of your... your itch is a symptom of your skin condition.
[SPEAKER_00]: In itself, it's not the issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can itch and scratch and so on, but unless you uproot the underlying cause, you're still under the same condition.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the sense of self, I am, I am not, will I be, all of that is already the result of that self-centeredness that we mentioned before.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only seeing, or basically, mostly seeing things through your own point of view that's fueled by greed, aversion, delusion, seeking the pleasure, avoiding pain, and distracting yourself from neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why sense-restraint, like virtue and sense-restraint, is already kind of forcing you to go against the grain of your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's actually psychologically frightening for people to, like, even if they're not celibate, just the idea of celibacy or the idea of not scratching their itch freaks them out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's like too much pain to bear, because their sense of self is so dependent upon those outlets.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you actually start practicing that, you are already undermining that gratuitous self-centeredness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your sense of self is diminishing, even if you don't necessarily, you know, measure it or you can quantify it or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not about finding the answer to what myself and this myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about uprooting things sufficiently enough until those six types of perceiving it are dissolved.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, what's left is with not-self, you see not-self.
That's it.